<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
        <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC5731 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5731.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC5730 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5730.xml">
        <!ENTITY AR-APP-1.0 SYSTEM "../application-1.0/application-1.0-ref.xml">
        ]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space (using these PIs as follows is recommended
   by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-ar-exAvail-epp-mapping-01"
     ipr="none" submissionType="independent">
    <front>
        <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary
         if the full title is longer than 39 characters -->

        <title abbrev="EPP Domain Extended availability Mapping">
            Domain Name Extended Availability Extension Mapping for the
            Extensible Provisioning
            Protocol (EPP)
        </title>

        <author fullname="James Mitchell" initials="J." surname="Mitchell">
            <organization>AusRegistry</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>8/10 Queens Road</street>
                    <city>Melbourne</city>
                    <region>Victoria</region>
                    <code>3004</code>
                    <country>AU</country>
                </postal>
                <email>james.mitchell@ausregistry.com</email>
                <uri>www.ausregistry.com</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Chris Wright" initials="C." surname="Wright">
            <organization>AusRegistry</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>8/10 Queens Road</street>
                    <city>Melbourne</city>
                    <region>Victoria</region>
                    <code>3004</code>
                    <country>AU</country>
                </postal>
                <email>chris@ausregistry.com</email>
                <uri>www.ausregistry.com</uri>
            </address>
        </author>

        <date month="May" year="2013"/>

        <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->
        <area>General</area>
        <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
        <keyword>EPP</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t>
                This document describes extensions to the Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP)
                for obtaining detailed availability information of domain names.
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">
            <t>
                The check command described in
                <xref target="RFC5731">EPP Domain Name Mapping</xref>
                provides a hint to determine a domain object's availability.
                This works well in providing basic information
                for the client to anticipate the success or failure of registering
                a domain using the &lt;create&gt; command.
                To provide a more rich user interface to potential registrants,
                clients require more detailed information regarding object availability
                than available through a binary yes/no response.
            </t>
            <t>
                This document describes extensions to the Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP)
                for clients to obtain extended details regarding the availability of domain names.
            </t>
            <t>
                This extension can be used when more detailed information is required
                about the availability of a domain name.
            </t>
            <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
                <t>
                    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
                    "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
                    this document are to be interpreted as described in
                    <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref><![CDATA[.]]>
                </t>
                <t>
                    "exAvail-1.0" is used as an abbreviation for
                    "urn:ar:params:xml:ns:exAvail-1.0". The XML namespace prefix
                    "exAvail" is used, but implementations MUST NOT depend on it and
                    instead employ a proper namespace-aware XML parser and serializer
                    to interpret and output the XML documents.
                </t>
                <t>In this document english words with letters of different cases are
                    used to indicate variants, even though these don't indicate variants
                    in a real registry.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Extended Availability Details">
            <t>
                To provide more details about the availability of a domain object,
                this extension adds additional elements to the
                <xref target="RFC5731">EPP Domain Name Mapping</xref><![CDATA[.]]>
                Only those new elements are described here.
            </t>
            <section title="State">
                <t>
                    The extended availability details of a domain name are
                    provided using the state element.
                    A MANDATORY "s" attribute describes the extended availability
                    state of the queried domain name.
                    The list of extended availability states with a description
                    of any child elements of this state element are provided below:
                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t>
                            available - The queried domain name is available to be
                            registered as a domain object with immediate effect.
                            If the registry is currently not accepting registrations,
                            the date and time from which the domain name can be
                            registered MAY be provided as a child element of this state.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            application - The queried domain name is available to
                            be registered only as a domain application object.
                            The identifier of the phase in which a domain application
                            can be submitted for this domain name is provided
                            in a child element.
                            If the registry is not currently accepting applications,
                            the date and time from which an application can be
                            submitted MAY be provided as a child element of this state.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            unavailable - The queried domain name meets the composition
                            requirements for domain names, however not available to
                            be registered as either a domain object or a domain
                            application object.
                            The reason of unavailability for this domain name MAY be
                            provided as a child element of this state.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            reserved - The queried domain name is reserved by server policy
                            and is not available for registration.
                            The server specific reason for the reservation of this label
                            MAY be provided as a child element of this state.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            invalid - The queried domain name does not meet the composition
                            requirements for domain names and is not available for
                            registration as either a domain object or a domain
                            application object.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            activatedVariant - The queried domain name is an activated
                            variant of another domain name in the repository.
                            The domain name that resulted in the activation of this variant
                            SHOULD be provided as a child 'primaryDomainName' element of this
                            state.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            blockedVariant - The queried domain name is a blocked
                            variant of another domain name in the repository.
                            The domain name that resulted in this variant
                            getting blocked SHOULD be provided as a child
                            'primaryDomainName' element.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            withheldVariant - The queried domain name is a withheld
                            variant of an existing domain name in the repository.
                            The domain name that resulted in this name being witheld
                            SHOULD be provided as a child 'primaryDomainName' element.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            pendingCreate - The queried domain name is available for
                            registration, however its approval is subject to the outcome
                            of an offline process. If the registry is not currently
                            accepting registrations, the date and time from which the
                            domain name can be registered MAY be provided as a child
                            element of this state.
                        </t>
                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Phase Identifier">
                <t>
                    The identifier of the phase in which an application
                    for the queried domain name can be submitted.
                    The phase identifier is as described in
                    <xref target="AR-APP-1.0">EPP Domain Application Mapping</xref>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Reason">
                <t>
                    The reason explaining the unavailability of the queried domain name.
                    This is provided when the extended availability of a domain name
                    is "unavailable" or "invalid" or "reserved"
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Primary Domain Name">
                <t>
                    The queried domain name will be unavailable if it is
                    an active, withheld or blocked variant of a domain object
                    that exists in the repository.
                    In such a case, the primary domain name of the variant is provided.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="EPP Command Mapping">
            <t>
                A detailed description of the EPP syntax and semantics can be found
                in the
                <xref target="RFC5731">EPP core protocol specification</xref><![CDATA[.]]>
                The command mappings described here are specifically for use in the
                Domain Name Extended Availability Check Extension.
            </t>
            <section title="EPP Query Commands">
                <t>
                    EPP provides three commands to retrieve object information:
                    &lt;check&gt; to determine if an object is known to the server,
                    &lt;info&gt; to retrieve detailed information associated with an
                    object, and &lt;transfer&gt; to retrieve object transfer status
                    information.
                </t>
                <section title="EPP &lt;check&gt; Command">
                    <t>
                        This extension defines additional elements to extend the EPP
                        &lt;check&gt; command and response to be used in conjunction with
                        the
                        <xref target="RFC5731">EPP Domain Name Mapping</xref><![CDATA[.]]>
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        To enable clients to obtain additional information about a domain names availability,
                        the &lt;domain:check&gt; command is extended
                        with a &lt;exAvail:check&gt; element, which signals a client's
                        intention to retrieve extended availability information.
                    </t>
                    <figure align="left">
                        <preamble>
                            Example &lt;check&gt; command requesting extended availability
                            details
                        </preamble>
                        <artwork>
                            <![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
  <command>
    <check>
      <check xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:domain-1.0">
        <name>domain-avail.tld</name>
        <name>domain-application.tld</name>
        <name>domain-inuse.tld</name>
        <name>domain-blocked-by-application.tld</name>
        <name>domain-reserved.tld</name>
        <name>domain-inval!d.tld</name>
        <name>domain-variant.tld</name>
        <name>domain-VaRiAnT.tld</name>
        <name>DOMAIN-variant.tld</name>
        <name>domain-pendingCreate.tld</name>
      </check>
    </check>
    <extension>
      <check xmlns="urn:ar:params:xml:ns:exAvail-1.0" />
    </extension>
    <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
  </command>
</epp>]]>
                        </artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>
                        When a &lt;check&gt; command containing the &lt;exAvail:check&gt;
                        element has been processed successfully, the server MUST NOT
                        respond with the &lt;domain:chkData&gt; element described in the
                        <xref target="RFC5731">EPP Domain Name Mapping</xref><![CDATA[.]]>
                        Instead, servers must respond with a &lt;exAvail:chkData&gt; element
                        that contains one &lt;exAvail:cd&gt; element for each domain name
                        present in the command. The &lt;exAvail:cd&gt; element contains the
                        following child elements:
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t>
                                A &lt;exAvail:name&gt; element containing a domain name from the
                                corresponding command. The order and composition of domain names
                                in the response MUST be the same as the order and composition of
                                domain names provided in the command, with exception to
                                transformations required of validating XML parsers.
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                A &lt;exAvail:state&gt; element containing the extended
                                availability details of the domain name.
                                A MANDATORY "s" attribute describes the extended
                                availability state of the queried domain name.
                                To describe the availability in more detail the
                                &lt;exAvail:state&gt; element MAY also contain one
                                of the following child elements depending on the state:
                                <list style="symbols">
                                    <t>
                                        An OPTIONAL &lt;exAvail:phase&gt; element containing the
                                        phase identifier of the phase in which an application
                                        can be submitted for the domain name.
                                        This information is only supplied when the domain name
                                        is available as an application.
                                    </t>
                                    <t>
                                        An OPTIONAL &lt;exAvail:date&gt; element containing
                                        the date time from which the domain name can be provisioned
                                        as a domain object or an application object.
                                        The type that the object can be provisioned as can
                                        be determined by the value of the &lt;exAvail:state&gt;
                                        element's "s" attribute.
                                        If this element exists, it is an indication that the
                                        domain name is not available at the time of the
                                        extended availability check query, but in the future
                                        from the date time of this element.
                                    </t>
                                    <t>
                                        An OPTIONAL &lt;exAvail:reason&gt; element containing
                                        the reason of unavailability.
                                        This element is provided when the domain is unavailable
                                        as it is blocked by another object in the repository or
                                        due to server policy i.e., when the domain extended
                                        availability state is "unavailable", "invalid" or "reserved".
                                    </t>
                                    <t>
                                        An OPTIONAL &lt;exAvail:primaryDomainName&gt; element
                                        containing the primary domain name of the variant
                                        that is blocking the provisioning of the domain name.
                                        This is provided when the domain name queried for
                                        is an active, withheld or blocked variant of a domain
                                        object that exists in the repository.
                                    </t>
                                </list>
                            </t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                    <figure>
                        <preamble>
                            Example &lt;check&gt; response containing the extended availability
                            details
                        </preamble>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<epp xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:epp-1.0">
<response>
 <result code="1000">
   <msg lang="en">Command completed successfully</msg>
 </result>
 <extension>
  <chkData xmlns:exAvail="urn:ar:params:xml:ns:exAvail-1.0">
  <cd>
   <name>domain-avail.tld</name>
   <state s="available">
    <date>2012-10-20T00:00:00Z</date>
   </state>
  </cd>
  <cd>
   <name>domain-application.tld</name>
   <state s="application">
    <phase>sunrise</exAvil:phase>
    <date>2012-10-20T00:00:00Z</date>
   </state>
  </cd>
  <cd>
   <name>domain-inuse.tld</name>
   <state s="unavailable">
    <reason>In use</reason>
   </state>
  </cd>
  <cd>
   <name>domain-blocked-by-application.tld</name>
   <state s="unavailable">
    <reason>Blocked by application</reason>
   </state>
  </cd>
  <cd>
   <name>domain-reserved.tld</name>
   <state s="reserved">
    <reason>ICANN Reserved</reason>
   </state>
  </cd>
  <cd>
   <name>domain-inval!d.tld</name>
   <state s="inValid">
    <reason>Invalid domain name</reason>
   </state>
  </cd>
  <cd>
   <name>domain-variant.tld</name>
   <state s="activatedVariant">
    <primaryDomainName>domain-VARIANT.tld</primaryDomainName>
   </state>
  </cd>
  <cd>
   <name>domain-VaRiAnT.tld</name>
   <state s="withheldVariant">
    <primaryDomainName>domain-VARIANT.tld</primaryDomainName>
   </state>
  </cd>
  <cd>
   <name>DOMAIN-variant.tld</name>
   <state s="blockedVariant">
    <primaryDomainName>domain-VARIANT.tld</primaryDomainName>
   </state>
  </cd>
  <cd>
   <name>domain-pendingCreate.tld</name>
   <state s="pendingCreate" />
  </cd>
 </chkData>
 </extension>
 <trID>
  <clTRID>ABC-12345</clTRID>
  <svTRID>57f39ac6-abd2-4fea-9a80-e791d1af86f7</svTRID>
 </trID>
</response>
</epp>]]>
                        </artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>
                <section title="EPP &lt;info&gt; Command">
                    <t>
                        This extension does not define any extension to the EPP
                        &lt;info&gt; command or response described in the
                        <xref target="RFC5731">EPP Domain Name Mapping</xref><![CDATA[.]]>
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="EPP &lt;transfer&gt; Command">
                    <t>
                        This extension does not define any extension to the EPP
                        &lt;transfer&gt; command or response described in the
                        <xref target="RFC5731">EPP Domain Name Mapping</xref><![CDATA[.]]>
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section title="EPP Transform Commands">
                <t>
                    EPP provides five commands to transform objects: &lt;create&gt;
                    to create an instance of an object, &lt;delete&gt; to delete an
                    instance of an object, &lt;renew&gt; to extend the validity period
                    of an object, &lt;transfer&gt; to manage object sponsorship
                    changes, and &lt;update&gt; to change information associated with
                    an object.
                </t>
                <section title="EPP &lt;create&gt; Command">
                    <t>
                        This extension does not define any extension to the EPP
                        &lt;create&gt; command or response described in the
                        <xref target="RFC5731">EPP Domain Name Mapping</xref><![CDATA[.]]>
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="EPP &lt;delete&gt; Command">
                    <t>
                        This extension does not define any extension to the EPP
                        &lt;delete&gt; command or response described in the
                        <xref target="RFC5731">EPP Domain Name Mapping</xref><![CDATA[.]]>
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="EPP &lt;renew&gt; Command">
                    <t>
                        This extension does not define any extension to the EPP
                        &lt;renew&gt; command or response described in the
                        <xref target="RFC5731">EPP Domain Name Mapping</xref><![CDATA[.]]>
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="EPP &lt;transfer&gt; Command">
                    <t>
                        This extension does not define any extension to the EPP
                        &lt;transfer&gt; command or response described in the
                        <xref target="RFC5731">EPP Domain Name Mapping</xref><![CDATA[.]]>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="EPP &lt;update&gt; Command">
                    <t>
                        This extension does not define any extension to the EPP
                        &lt;update&gt; command or response described in the
                        <xref target="RFC5731">EPP Domain Name Mapping</xref><![CDATA[.]]>
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>
            </section>
            <section title="Formal Syntax">
                <t>
                    An EPP object mapping is specified in XML Schema notation. The
                    formal syntax presented here is a complete schema representation of
                    the object mapping, suitable for automated validation of EPP XML
                    instances.
                </t>
                <figure align="left">
                <artwork> <![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<schema targetNamespace="urn:ar:params:xml:ns:exAvail-1.0"
        xmlns:exAvail="urn:ar:params:xml:ns:exAvail-1.0"
        xmlns:eppcom="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:eppcom-1.0"
        xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
        elementFormDefault="qualified">

 <import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:eppcom-1.0"/>

 <!-- Custom Extensions found in EPP commands. -->
 <element name="check"/>

 <!-- Child response elements.-->
 <element name="chkData" type="exAvail:chkDataType"/>

 <complexType name="chkDataType">
        <sequence>
            <element name="cd" type="exAvail:checkType"
                     maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
        </sequence>
 </complexType>

 <complexType name="checkType">
    <sequence>
        <element name="name" type="eppcom:labelType"/>
        <element name="state" type="exAvail:checkStateType"/>
    </sequence>
 </complexType>

 <complexType name="checkStateType">
    <choice>
        <sequence>
            <element name="reason" type="eppcom:reasonType"
                     minOccurs="0"/>
        </sequence>
        <sequence>
            <element name="phase" type="eppcom:labelType"
                     minOccurs="0"/>
            <element name="date" type="dateTime"
                     minOccurs="0"/>
        </sequence>
        <sequence>
            <element name="primaryDomainName"
                     type="eppcom:labelType"/>
        </sequence>
        </choice>
        <attribute name="s" type="exAvail:stateValueType"
                   use="required"/>
 </complexType>

 <simpleType name="stateValueType">
    <restriction base="token">
        <enumeration value="available"/>
        <enumeration value="application"/>
        <enumeration value="unavailable"/>
        <enumeration value="reserved"/>
        <enumeration value="invalid"/>
        <enumeration value="activatedVariant"/>
        <enumeration value="withheldVariant"/>
        <enumeration value="blockedVariant"/>
        <enumeration value="pendingCreate"/>
    </restriction>
 </simpleType>
</schema>]]>
                    </artwork>
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section title="Security Considerations">
                <t>
                    The mapping extensions described in this document do not provide any
                    security services beyond those described by
                    <xref target="RFC5730">EPP</xref><![CDATA[,]]>
                    the
                    <xref target="RFC5731">EPP Domain Name Mapping</xref><![CDATA[,]]>
                    and protocol layers used by EPP. The security considerations
                    described in these other specifications also apply to this
                    specification.
                </t>
            </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            &RFC2119;
            &RFC5731;
            &RFC5730;
        </references>
        <references title="Informative References">
            &AR-APP-1.0;
        </references>
    </back>
</rfc>